[SPEAKER_01]: So, I have several suttas about energy and effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have a kind of general discussion about that and what I mean when the Buddha says that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, first thing I'll read is from Sanyutta Nikaya, the Bhojanga Sanyutta, the third sutta.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's on the enlightenment factors.
[SPEAKER_01]: Says, starts off, bhikkhus, those bhikkhus who are accomplished in virtue, accomplished in composure, accomplished in wisdom, accomplished in liberation, accomplished in knowledge and vision of liberation, even the sight of those bhikkhus is helpful.
[SPEAKER_01]: I say, even listening to them, even approaching them,
[SPEAKER_01]: Even attending on them, even recollecting them, even going forth after them is helpful.
[SPEAKER_01]: I say, for what reason?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when one has heard the dhamma from such a bhikkhu, one dwells withdrawn by two... one of two kinds of... by way of two kinds of withdrawal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Withdrawal of the body and withdrawal of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dwelling thus withdrawn, one recollects the dhamma and thinks it over.
[SPEAKER_01]: On that occasion, the enlightenment factor of mindfulness is aroused by the bhikkhu.
[SPEAKER_01]: On that occasion, the bhikkhu develops the enlightenment factor of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: On that occasion, the enlightenment factor of mindfulness comes to fulfillment by development in that bhikkhu.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dwelling thus mindfully, he discriminates that dhamma with wisdom, examines it, makes an investigation of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And whenever he does that, he's mindfully developing the discrimination of states or investigation factor.
[SPEAKER_01]: While he discriminates that dhamma with wisdom and examines it, his energy is aroused without slackening.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whenever a bhikkhu's energy is aroused without slackening, as he investigates the dhamma with wisdom and examines it, on that occasion, the enlightenment factor of energy is aroused by the bhikkhu.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, after that, it says, eh... when his energy is aroused, there arises in him spirit, eh... epīti, eh... translated rapture, usually.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whenever bhikkhu's rapture arises in bhikkhu, energy... his energy is aroused, on that occasion, eh... this alignment factor of rapture is aroused.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll stop after this one for a bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: For one whose mind is uplifted by rapture, the body becomes tranquil and the mind becomes tranquil.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh... it sounds very like, you know, at first glance, you kind of think of energy as always this kind of, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: Like kind of over-energized.
[SPEAKER_01]: That seems to be the usual kind of assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's here saying that it's clearly within kind of the framework of... well, it's also for... what's the sake of that applying energy?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's for having a certain kind of tranquility.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then people overthink, overdo tranquility too.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh... as far as that goes, eh... eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: What is that... what exactly is that kind of energy that allows for one to be tranquil and not to be like that kind of assumption that we have of just like too much?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it's not... it's not an inspiration to do something, which is usually requires too much.
[SPEAKER_02]: Requires you to be externally inspired, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: Find external reasons that will motivate you to do things.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's more like the recognition from the... well, the recognition of the right view, first of all.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then... because, see, the work that you need to do, in terms of freeing yourself from suffering, is nowhere else, except within your presently enduring situation, whatever that is.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not in the future, it's not in the past.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's right here.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you're not free from suffering right here, right now, it's because right here, right now, you're still entertaining craving, or the view of craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, once you actually discern that that work is not just that it's not elsewhere, you also discern that it's very doable.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's the recognition of that doability of the things you still need to do, the ones that still hasn't fulfilled the goal of Arahantship,
[SPEAKER_02]: Naturally gives the energy to do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, you know, like, if you have something that you need to do, that's really, like, it requires so much preparation, so far away in the future, it's hard to get motivated to do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But when you recognize that doing this is literally only on you and up to you and within you, it doesn't require anything, anyone outside.
[SPEAKER_02]: Same with tranquility as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not practicing tranquility in order to be... not being bothered by this person or by that person.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just a natural calmness, because you realize it's entirely up to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, of course, you would want to develop it, because it's obviously very agreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it sounds to me also like it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like something that... it's not like... it has to be almost like a steady kind of thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I'll read the other sutta I was going to mention.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the one that's quite...
[SPEAKER_01]: This is in the Anguttara book of sixes, number 55, Bhikkhu Sona.
[SPEAKER_01]: While the Venerable Sona was alone in seclusion, the following course of thought arose in his mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am one of the Blessed One's most energetic disciples, yet my mind has not been liberated from the taints by non-singing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, there is wealth in my family, and it is possible for me to enjoy my wealth and do meritorious deeds.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let me then give up the training and return to lower life, so that I can enjoy my wealth and do meritorious deeds.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha, having known this course of thought in Sona's mind, went and appeared to him, and asked him if he was thinking that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sona says, yes, Bhante.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, the Buddha asks, tell me, Sona, in the past, when you lived at home, weren't you skilled at the lute?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, Bhante.
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you think, Sona?
[SPEAKER_01]: When its strings were too tight, was your lute well-tuned and easy to play?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, Bhante.
[SPEAKER_01]: When its strings were too loose, was your lute well-tuned and easy to play?
[SPEAKER_01]: But, Sona, when its strings were neither too tight nor too loose, but adjusted to a balanced pitch, was your lute well-tuned and easy to play?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, Bhante.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, too, Sona, if energy is aroused too forcefully, this leads to restlessness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if energy is too lax, this leads to laziness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Therefore, Sona, resolve on a balance of energy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Achieve evenness of spiritual faculties and take... pick up your sign there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pick up the sign of that, you might translate it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you... if you get the energy to do the work, if you lose the context, if you lose perspective on account of it, you'll become restless.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you don't, you won't.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, he's so keen to uproot the craving, that he gave in to craving for uprooting it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, that the energy to do it, by losing the right context in regard to it, he turned it into craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it became restlessness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or same, the energy to become... the intention to become,
[SPEAKER_02]: If you lose the context of it, it becomes just lazy, careless, drowsy, sleepy, whatever else.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you keep the context, then it's just calm energy.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that's what means they're getting... maintaining the balance means maintaining the context.
[SPEAKER_02]: As to the... like... what the purpose of energy is, what the purpose of tranquility is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, in order to do that, it's a matter of kind of...
[SPEAKER_02]: Maintaining mindfulness in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why you can't have too much of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, in a sense, it sounds as though, like, while you're doing whatever efforts you're doing, it's almost like... good to, like, really kind of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, well, I'm thinking...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm going this route.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why don't I check on the perspective of things now?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, it's not... it's not up to you to decide.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I need energy now.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, you can discern that, sure, if that's what the situation dictates.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you can't go, oh, let me just develop some energy.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you want to recognize, first, of course, the mindful context, as in, what is the purpose of all of this?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's freedom from craving, always.
[SPEAKER_02]: It never, never, never steers away from that purpose.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, do you feel
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, clear about the direction of freedom from craving?
[SPEAKER_02]: If you're clear enough, in a way, then okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, keep the... keep the context in your mind, in a sense, of the purposes to be free from craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I need to understand craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how can I make the effort to understand the craving without needing to crave for that effort, without needing to wind myself up in order to do it now?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how can I get the energy without allowing that energy to make me restless?
[SPEAKER_02]: By, again, not losing the right order of mindfulness, not losing the sight of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you find out that it's more important to not act out of craving, even if you haven't understood craving yet.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's when you forget that that's more important, you then choose to make more important, let me just act out of this craving, and then I'll figure it out, and then I'll never crave again.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you end up just revolving in a vicious circle, because you yourself maintain the craving in order to understand the way out of craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the way out of craving is by cessation of craving, not by understanding it on your own terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you believe, then, say, you want to contemplate something and you don't want to,
[SPEAKER_01]: If you feel muddled about the intention behind that... You need to know the intention behind, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I want to contemplate this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is it because I want to get rid of the unpleasantness of craving?
[SPEAKER_02]: Means you're acting out of craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, no, I don't...
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't feel anything unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: I just want to invest some effort into, like, you know, steering a few things up to, you know, to create a work, because the mind was a bit dull.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, if your mind is not dull, then it's just too tight.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then you actually want to be... No, I will not lose perspective.
[SPEAKER_02]: See, not acting out of craving does not automatically mean, oh, I'll just go and sleep and be lazy and drowsy.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't.
[SPEAKER_02]: It just means you don't lose the mindfulness, you don't sacrifice the priority of mindful context on account of what you want to do, even if it's to understand craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you're not sure why you're trying to understand the craving, as in, is this rooted in trying to get rid of the suffering, or is it maybe root means, your doubtful means, you should calm yourself first.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you calm yourself first by maintaining absence of craving is more important than acting out of craving even for the sake of getting rid of the craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you are responsible for absence of craving or for presence of craving, because craving needs action to be maintained.
[SPEAKER_02]: You need to act out of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you're not acting out of it, you realize, okay, that's all I need to do, for now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, when there is no pressure of craving, then the mind can maybe think, if it wants to still think about these things, but often you realize, the only reason you want to understand craving was just to get rid of the pain that was currently felt.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's already rooted in craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, don't lose the context, for example, on the unpleasantness of restlessness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, it will become the energy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or the unpleasantness of kind of being dull.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, it will become tranquility.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't need to...
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't have anything happening all the time, or all the time figuring things out.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, why do I, by default, habitually, try to get rid of this unpleasantness?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's because you still prioritize your views, that I must be doing this, I must be doing that, I must be getting rid of this.
[SPEAKER_02]: But even that is rooted in simply wanting to be free from suffering by being free from craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, why do you go around creating craving that makes you suffer, in order to be free from it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Initially, yeah, everybody has to do that, but the point is to come when you recognize that, okay, now, if the mind is free from craving, all I need to do is stay mindful with that, and then make sure that it doesn't turn into craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: You protect it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't need to constantly sort of prod it, and prod it, and prod it, because again, it will become too tight.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, what do you think in terms of, like, things that people can pick up on?
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, it says, like, picking up the signs of when the mind is too much like this or too much like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, obviously, you know, inevitably, people are going to make the mistakes and go too far one way or the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, it seems that the Buddha's saying is important to, like, recognize, oh, when this is in fact happening, discern when that is happening.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: When you discern when that's happening, when you discern the context of your action, of what you're about to do, of what you're engaged in,
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't, like, preemptively discern it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, look, look, look, it's here.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's not necessarily a problem in itself.
[SPEAKER_02]: The problem is, as I said, when, on account of your energy slash restlessness, you try to get rid of the pain through acting out of pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you maintain the craving in regard to it, which is going to make you more restless.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you're... it requires it for its own... for that very action.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you discern what's present.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, is this my situation?
[SPEAKER_02]: Am I trying to get rid of... Am I trying to understand craving now?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because I just want to get rid of the discomfort of restlessness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or, am I trying to understand the dhamma because it's really unpleasant when my mind is like not thinking about anything?
[SPEAKER_02]: No engagement.
[SPEAKER_02]: It frightens me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Discerning that, it's already a step forward to not act out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't, like, make a checklist of signs to pick up...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what signs are.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why they're, like, these generic names, signs and tokens.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just characteristics of what's there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what is the main context?
[SPEAKER_02]: What is the characteristic of the main context here is, fundamentally, I'm just acting out of suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm trying to get rid of this unpleasant state of
[SPEAKER_02]: Whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: Dullness, non-thinking and whatnot, just mind is a bit slow.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't like it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I feel guilty, feel bad.
[SPEAKER_02]: I feel I must do this, I must do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because this is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you end up acting out of the same principle that people act throughout their life, which is a principle that keeps you bound to the action.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's when you recognize... No, hold on.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm not acting...
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm not engaging in anything by wholesome, by body, by speech, by mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the dullness of the mind is not my dullness.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't need to be my problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just a phenomenon there, as the current state of mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's when satipaṭṭhāna sutta is done rightly.
[SPEAKER_02]: The mindfulness on the level of the mind would be...
[SPEAKER_02]: He knows his mind as elated mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Elated mind as elated mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: He knows his depressed mind as depressed mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: He knows his dull mind as dull mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Quick mind as quick mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sharp, sharp, slow, slow.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just a state of mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's you who tries to get rid of it on account of discomfort it might cause you.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, stop acting from out of the way you feel.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the same principle that's kind of common to energy turning into restlessness or calmness turning into sloth and torpor.
[SPEAKER_02]: Losing the context in regard to how it makes you feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right when you said that, I realized that I had been just fighting off dullness the whole time of this talk, and that's why I was having trouble formulating more questions.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I was like, why is this happening?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sometimes you're slower, sometimes you're faster.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: What matters is losing the context on account of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you lose the context when you choose to engage.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I must get rid of this dullness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or, I'll give in to the dullness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or, I must get rid of the... the...
[SPEAKER_02]: Restlessness or I'll give in to restlessness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Either way, you engage with it.
[SPEAKER_02]: How about I can stay mindful in regard to how I feel about the restlessness or while I'm restless.
[SPEAKER_02]: How I feel while I'm slow.
[SPEAKER_02]: How I feel while I'm doubtful.
[SPEAKER_02]: How I feel while there is central inclination.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because either... that's what's in common to all the hindrances, by the way, is acting on account of pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sensuality is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: You act towards it, to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It will... it's like a sting, it's unpleasant, so you want to act out, lash out, to get rid of it, to replace it, to retaliate.
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, if... if it were not felt unpleasantly, you wouldn't be acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And same for the other hindrances, doubt as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: You try to figure things out, not because they need figuring out or because you lack clarity or not enough information about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's simply because doubtful state is very unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you're just trying to get rid of how you feel on one level by acting on a completely different level of figuring this out that will then make me feel good.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if it does so, you still acted out of the way you felt.
[SPEAKER_02]: And as such, you still remain fully pressured, subjected, contacted by the feeling, which means you always will be, for as long as you keep maintaining that type of action.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you want to learn how to act without needing to act out of your feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you learn how to act without needing to act out of your feeling by recognizing what's already there that doesn't require you or your action.
[SPEAKER_02]: Dull mind is already there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sharp mind is already there at times.
[SPEAKER_02]: Pleasant feeling is already there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Unpleasant feeling is already there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Look, body is already there.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're holding the tablet, scratching your arm, whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not thinking.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't need to attend to every second.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's already happening.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you don't need to stop it in order to recognize it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just need to realize that there's a whole domain of things already happening that do not require your volition, your interference, your greed, your aversion, your delusion, your views, your assumptions.
[SPEAKER_02]: Completely redundant.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's learning to see that domain as actually more fundamental than the domain of your volition, your choices, your wishes, your desires, your assumptions, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: You said to check how you feel in regards to a thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not so much saying like...
[SPEAKER_01]: In a way, it's almost obvious that, yeah, it's going to be painful, but like, how do I feel about the pain is more important perhaps.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like what I asked you the other day.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, so what's your kind of mood?
[SPEAKER_02]: My kind of mood is a bit unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: How do you feel about that mood?
[SPEAKER_02]: Do you feel like, oh, this mood is unpleasant and I must understand it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Means that's what your mood is, really.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's how you feel in regard to your mood, is where your mood is.
[SPEAKER_01]: I thought you were just saying, maybe you aren't so bothered by the pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: At that time, you might say, oh, I feel kind of okay about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it's okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's unpleasant, but... doesn't need to be anything more than that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Unless you lose the sight of it, and then... automatically start leaning towards trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, as far as these energies go, you know, we're talking about energy and energy and stuff, it's obviously...
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing mystical about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in terms of, like, the, you know, when the Buddha talked about energy, then what are we exactly referring to?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'll read the four right strivings there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Effort, willingness, readiness for effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what energy is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's almost like not always the act of preparedness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, you're ready.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I can...
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't need to spend three hours thinking, oh, I need to do this work.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, just, oh, work needs to be done, I do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: No work needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm still energetic.
[SPEAKER_02]: Without needing to act and kind of engage with things because I'm so full of energy.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have energy means you are ready to act properly.
[SPEAKER_02]: If lust, you're ready to not entertain it.
[SPEAKER_02]: If non-lust, you're ready to protect it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's why energy, rightly, with the right context, it's effortless.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's all you're doing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how is this tireless energy?
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what tireless energy is exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't tire you.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't need to be tiring yourself out of that energy.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just endless energy because it's... it's an endless readiness.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that is a state of mind independent of your action.
[SPEAKER_02]: It depends on your understanding and the context, the clarity of the context.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's four great strivings that...
[SPEAKER_01]: Here bhikkhus, a bhikkhu generates desire for the non-arising of unarisen evil and wholesome states.
[SPEAKER_01]: He makes an effort, arouses energy, applies his mind and strives.
[SPEAKER_01]: He generates for the abandoning of arisen evil and wholesome states.
[SPEAKER_01]: He makes an effort, so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: He generates for the arising of unarisen wholesome states.
[SPEAKER_01]: He makes an effort, arouses energy, applies his mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: He generates desire for the maintenance of arisen wholesome states, for their non-decay, increase, expansion, and fulfillment by development.
[SPEAKER_01]: These are the four right strivings.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you mentioned, like, an effortless energy preparedness kind of thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's to say...
[SPEAKER_01]: I lost the question, because mine is still there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, no, it's all right.
[SPEAKER_02]: If done rightly, arousing that energy against the backdrop of the right context, it's same like with the arising of maintenance of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's effortless and it's also not unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you need to arouse the energy and it feels like a chore and it's unpleasant, means there is the element of restlessness that bothers you, means you're acting out of craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, why?
[SPEAKER_02]: You ask yourself, why do you need to arouse energy then?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, regain the context for energy.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not sense of duty or because somebody said or because I must be energetic.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then it's... you can't sustain that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then it's like, why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why do I need to arise energy?
[SPEAKER_02]: And when it says why?
[SPEAKER_02]: To dispel the unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, so are there unwholesome states that need dispelling?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: So what am I arising energy for?
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe I'm already energetic.
[SPEAKER_02]: I just don't see it because I turn it into restlessness by default.
[SPEAKER_02]: As in, I am ready to deal with things when they come.
[SPEAKER_02]: That doesn't mean you keep going inviting them to come.
[SPEAKER_02]: Quite the opposite.
[SPEAKER_02]: You learn to recognize, when they're not there, then, okay, now it's a different energy.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not the energy, I must deal with this, because there's nothing to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I just must protect this.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you protect it, by not trying to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you're getting a sense of, like, sometimes...
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, it almost seems like an obvious thing, like, you know, you're a little bit dull, a little bit tired.
[SPEAKER_01]: The obvious thing that surfaces, you just kind of rouse yourself, but it's not always necessarily the right thing to be doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, of course not.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like passing out or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I feel drowsy and tired.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm not sure why.
[SPEAKER_02]: I just feel that way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, is it a problem?
[SPEAKER_02]: Am I giving in to lust on account of this?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Am I giving in to anger, ill will on account of this?
[SPEAKER_02]: Am I performing actions of distracting nature on account of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, that's all I need to do.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not give in to these things.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't need to get rid of this, because I didn't have seen its arising.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you realize, maybe because you didn't sleep well last night.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe because you're tired.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe because you didn't eat enough.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe because you're sick.
[SPEAKER_02]: Who knows what the reason is?
[SPEAKER_02]: Doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: What matters is why do you act out of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I must always get rid of the fatigue and tiredness.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's impossible, because the body gets fatigued and tired.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just don't want to act out of, ah... losing the context.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't want to act out of habit, out of a duty, out of a whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's usually a habit, because in the beginning you don't really can't see the threshold of the hindrances, so then everything and nothing is a problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: When the problem is there, you don't see it.
[SPEAKER_02]: When the problem is not there, you make it into a problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, inevitably, you have to work your way through that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the point has to come when you recognize that, yeah, okay, I'm dull, I'm tired, I can't think.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's not the problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: The problem is when I choose to act towards greed, towards ill-will, aversion, hatred, towards distraction, carelessness, out of this feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's a clear choice.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you just don't act there.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you don't need to do anything with it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You mentioned before, like... And, by the way, same if, like, I must figure this out.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, because I want to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I'm acting out of it, just on the level of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you mentioned, like, if there's doubt or ambiguity, it's kind of probably on that side of things.
[SPEAKER_02]: What do you mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you want to... you want to accomplish something, you want to do something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: Almost like you're finding different reasons, so you're not really finding the right reason.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yeah, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not even clear as to why.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just keep looking for something to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you just look for... almost like you're just in your mind starting to give justifications.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, well, that's like acting out of doubt, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: See, like, you can, as I said many times before, you can only doubt the content of your experience, of your thoughts, of the idea, whatever you're doubtful about.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you can't doubt that you're experiencing nature of doubt, that you're under the pressure of doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: You cannot
[SPEAKER_02]: But losing the sight that that's what's first, that that's where the problem is, you then give in to try to clarify the content, deal with the content, re-explain the content, revisit the content, re-read the content, hash out the content again, because it doesn't make me feel right.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't make you feel right, because doubt is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't want to feel unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's really a question of... well, you should... if you're being affected by the doubt, that's the first question.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if it is, and that's... that's the work that you've been mentioning.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the work sounds like it's not what you assume the work has to be at any given time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You may well be, like, looking past where the work already is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: More often than not, I think that's the case.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you act out of this... or this is what... No.
[SPEAKER_02]: My work is determined by what's presently enduring.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not by what my sense of duty dictates.
[SPEAKER_02]: And even it's like, okay, so sense of duty.
[SPEAKER_02]: How did I acquire that sense of duty?
[SPEAKER_02]: And you realize you acquired it before you were aware of any context.
[SPEAKER_02]: When you just adopted it as as a must, on account of faith, on account of external instruction.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is fine, but if you remain bound to it, you remain bound to sīla bhārmasa.
[SPEAKER_02]: Acting out of the sense of duty without actually discernment of what's presently there and what presently it's addressing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means you won't be seeing the mind free from lust as mind free from lust.
[SPEAKER_02]: You won't be seeing mind affected with lust as mind affected with lust.
[SPEAKER_02]: And with anger and distraction.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you're just acting out sense of duty, always, regardless of what the state of mind is.
[SPEAKER_02]: And by doing so, you end up appropriating your state of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you have anything you wanted to bring?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes, I've seen the translation for energy as zeal, and it made me think of the first sutta you had read.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, seeing a teacher or accomplished bhikkhus, instead of, like, having this arousal of energy, more of a zeal, in the sense of confidence,
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, recognizing.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's like in the other suttas, when it says, you know, a man interested in his own welfare, he goes and visits wise men, and then he lends the ear, understand what they say, then he measures the task.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like a prerequisite for the zeal.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, this is what needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't be zealous about a task when you have no idea.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I'll just do everything and nothing.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll just pray.
[SPEAKER_02]: Meditate, watch my nostril, and then the work will be done for me.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know exactly, you know exactly what needs to be done to free yourself from suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, so, that's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's doable by knowing what needs to be done, you make it doable.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then the energy will arise from it, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Could that also be like a sense of urgency?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like seeing that... Well, say, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I think sense of urgency would be more of like a, you know, a prod that would result in energy.
[SPEAKER_02]: But yeah, yeah, it's connected to that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's exactly connected to that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, like, oh, no, just, oh, there's this world that needs to be done, but I can afford to not do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, you recognize, oh, it needs to be done, and now I know what it is, and it's like, it's a must.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's an imperative.
[SPEAKER_02]: You will have to do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But because now you recognize for what it is, it doesn't feel like this ambiguous sort of non-defined chore that oppresses you, but you can't really put your finger on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know exactly what suffering is, what freedom from suffering is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Psst!
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't eat the leech.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know exactly what suffering is, what freedom from suffering is, and you know exactly what to do to develop it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that, yeah, that's why the right view needs to come first.
[SPEAKER_02]: Otherwise, there is no right effort without right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then people... then the effort, if it's not in line with right view, the effort is wrong, and it could be just because of that, sort of like, oh, I feel unpleasant feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you know... if you have that understanding of that,
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you're sitting close to that, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But not just, oh, I must, I must act out of this, get rid of this.
[SPEAKER_02]: You recognize that you're acting on account of how you feel, which means craving has to be there.
[SPEAKER_02]: You, you know, you can't directly seek, oh, this is my craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you can know based on the inclination towards the present enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: Am I trying to get rid of this?
[SPEAKER_02]: Means I am craving against it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I am the craving against it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I am the craving for it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's why you can't just... oh, just be present, just be here, just always do the same thing, because it's not... mind is not always in the same state.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can act for the right reason, but not... but acting just because of the feeling, that is the wrong reason.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's going to make it wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why you're still not going to be freeing yourself from craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: You might, oh, well, it's my duty to contemplate and do walking meditation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you need something to do, because you're restless, because it's unpleasant, because you want to get rid of the pain, or because you really want to maintain the state that's free from craving, that you understood so.
[SPEAKER_01]: That seems like a lot of the work to me, like making... working to not have work, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's why you start doing it rightly, it ceases to be work.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why you say, oh, they practice the dhamma, you know, full of joy and delight, because it's effortless.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, again, you invest the work in adjusting the strings of your lute, but once you get them right, it's just effortless.
[SPEAKER_02]: Music just flows.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you only adjust it when it needs to be adjusted.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not all, just part of you playing is adjusting it, and that's not playing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, for example, let's say, the sutta, like, there's this one, the Majjhima-Nikāya, I don't have it with me here, the one where I mentioned, like, the, you know, the ways of stilling or calming, I don't know how you want to... Ah, removal of distracting thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how it's translated.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, that one, I think, a lot of people kind of misinterpret that as, like...
[SPEAKER_01]: I do this when this is here.
[SPEAKER_02]: I do that... Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: That means, either way, you keep acting on account of unpleasantness or
[SPEAKER_02]: And that is on the level of doing, which is why it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a duty.
[SPEAKER_02]: I have to do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I have to respond to this.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that way, it's always going to be a burden.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you do it rightly, it's not on the level of doing.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's on the level of discerning, which is effortless.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because things you discern are already there.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't need to develop them, create them, or, like, you know, bring them back or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: They're there.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just need to stop distracting yourself from them, through your efforts of doing them.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why people try too hard to be mindful.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why you're not mindful.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you're looking at the wrong place.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mindfulness is not on the level of the doing.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's on the level of intention behind your doing.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's on the level of presently enduring feeling, which is a basis for your doing.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's on the level of the presently enduring mood or the body, which is a basis for your action.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yet, here you are.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm mindful.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're doing it and that's why you're not mindful.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in terms that it sounds like it's something like, okay, you have... you are properly enduring whatever unwholesome thought has arisen, and then, kind of, these features, you've read about them, they will become apparent, because you're not... Yeah, because now you're providing the basis for those features to be discerned, because they are on those levels, but you were not seeing it, because you were not familiar enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in a sense of speaking, it's not like...
[SPEAKER_01]: Choosing is not the right term, in terms of how people do you think I'm gonna choose now to respond like this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, it's not.
[SPEAKER_02]: It precedes your choice.
[SPEAKER_02]: It even precedes your attention, in a way.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why I keep saying, like, mindfulness is about discerning the context, knowing what's already there,
[SPEAKER_02]: Without needing to attend to it, to know that's already there.
[SPEAKER_02]: The only reason you can attend to what you feel, is because you're already feeling it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means there's already a recognition of what's being felt.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you choose to ignore that, put that second, you choose to compromise that by allowing... No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Still, when I attend to it, now I know it's there.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you already knew what was there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Same with the body.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't need to keep attending to yourself that you're seated now.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're just seated.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if I were to ask you, out of the blue, what's your body position?
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm seated.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now you can choose to attend to it as well, but the only reason is because you already know that you're seated.
[SPEAKER_02]: So it's discerning that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Knowledge without attending it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you have to resist the need to attend it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And learn to discern what you already know and not...
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, I know, but I'll still attend it.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: That means you won't know it on the same level, because you chose still to act out of what you attend, as in what you chose.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you still want to make things to be on your own terms.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's that kind of compulsive bit that some people might need to restrain.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, even when you know, you still choose to give in to, okay, now let me attend it and reconfirm what I already know.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, oh, let me still allow myself to act out of how I feel, that I already know how I feel, but I want to act out of it anyway.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's your own dependence on your own craving that you're fully responsible for and you're maintaining through that type of action.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right, that's like your recent talk about the mindful...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know how recent it is... mindful forgetting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, forgetting properly means not remembering wrongly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's related.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, in terms of like, you know, mindfulness brings composure, that composure and that base, it's like on the level of that mindfulness, not that's something like you think, oh, now composure is like more known.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or more attentive or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just more of an unshakable context.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what composure is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, say, it's more, almost like, durable, it includes more.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Less perturbable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not that it's always on your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: It just remains there and it doesn't get perturbed by things you do attend or choose to do within that.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why an arahant, who has mindfulness that's imperturbable to its fullness, still speaks, talks, goes to toilet, eats, whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: Cannot be discerned externally.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, look, he's gliding in the air because he's an arahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, you can't tell him apart.
[SPEAKER_02]: Often they couldn't.
[SPEAKER_02]: Often other arahants couldn't tell him apart.
[SPEAKER_02]: They had to talk and see what the understanding is, how to understand it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, yeah, his mind is most likely free.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even the Buddha couldn't always tell.
[SPEAKER_02]: He said, yeah, he's free maybe, but if there's some residue left, you know, a little bit somewhere, unspecified, who knows to what extent, he'll be reborn in those great heavens and then become a non-returner.
[SPEAKER_02]: So it's again, it's about
[SPEAKER_02]: Developing that kind of context, discernment, which is what your mindfulness is, to the extent necessary, for, like, removal of any basis for acting out of greed, out of aversion, hatred, carelessness, out of distraction, boredom, all the unwholesome things.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why they're unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what would you... what would you refer to when you say carelessness?
[SPEAKER_01]: What are you referring to there?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I think that, like, carelessness would be...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you know you're a bit muddled.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know... there might be some, like, laziness present.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, you lose context of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you don't necessarily go straight into, oh, I'll just do something lustful or angry.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you start drifting away.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I'll just go and hang out for the sake of chit-chat.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not sensual chit-chat, but still.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I'll just go and, you know, find some random work, because I need something to do.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's already acting out of carelessness and distraction.
[SPEAKER_02]: Almost like not clarifying your intentions enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, I don't know, it's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: It'll be fine, or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Choosing to ignore.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I'll be alright.
[SPEAKER_02]: I can handle it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I can, I can, I can sort of, eh...
[SPEAKER_02]: Absorb this.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll be fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, see, the problem is that you lose the context on account of it, and that's why you're not fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if you, yeah, don't go further in your careless actions, nevertheless, you gave in to that extent.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's why, you know, even somebody who has understood the dhamma can can distract himself from fulfilling that understanding by work, what was the other one?
[SPEAKER_02]: Sleep and talk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a lot of work that doesn't need to be... like, it's not end of the world or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, it must be done and then you just enjoy doing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, like, building things up, repairing things that don't really... they're not to the point of repair.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or just finding things to do, finding activity, finding engagement, finding projects.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's the hard thing for me, like, kind of choosing when and where to actually start investigating my intentions, because there's almost...
[SPEAKER_01]: I have this inclination that I have to check every thought, and it's just not possible, not sustainable.
[SPEAKER_02]: Of course, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just going to wind you up quite unpleasantly, because you keep trying to control the uncontrollable.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, let me check this, let me check... Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why am I checking this?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, let me attend to this, let me attend to this, let me attend to this, let me...
[SPEAKER_02]: Why are you attending to it?
[SPEAKER_02]: To discern the knowledge that precedes your attention?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's why more often than not, it's actually people too keen to get rid of things even at the pretext of practicing the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's why calmness requires learning.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like samatha requires learning, requires understanding what samatha is, as the suttas often say.
[SPEAKER_02]: The monks who are not skilled, they should go and ask those monks that are skilled in calming their mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: How do I calm my mind?
[SPEAKER_02]: What do I attend?
[SPEAKER_02]: How do I regard saṅkharas in order to calm my mind?
[SPEAKER_02]: How do I calm my mind?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not like, oh, yeah, you just feel one with the universe.
[SPEAKER_02]: Accidentally.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, you know exactly what calmness is.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you start cultivating those signs.
[SPEAKER_02]: By not acting, by not giving in, by attending this, attending... Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: By knowing why you want to do before you do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: How do I attend saṅkharas?
[SPEAKER_02]: How do I attend the determinate containers for my attention, for my action?
[SPEAKER_02]: Tell me how to regard them, so I'm not pulled by my attention, by my action.
[SPEAKER_01]: How to regard them?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: How to maintain the context in regard to them?
[SPEAKER_00]: How to not lose the sight of them?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why, why, as I said before, why would you be acting out of...
[SPEAKER_02]: I need to attend every thought?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because the context of it, not attending, is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you obviously lost the sight of it, because now you're trying to control it through attending and investigating every second of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's all rooted in the same context that's still there.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that context is the saṅkhara of all of your actions.
[SPEAKER_02]: It determines the direction of every single action you do on account of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how do I then
[SPEAKER_02]: Regain the right perspective on those saṅkharas.
[SPEAKER_02]: How do I regard them?
[SPEAKER_02]: And then I won't be pulled by things that I'm attending to, or needing to, or pressured by those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, it seems like the most kind of straightforward to the point one is like, like, discerning how you, as we said before, how do I feel about the... this, like, intention that I'm doing?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I doing it because I really, like, feel a need to do it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, clarifying motivation behind your actions is already the beginning of samatha, because it's already the beginning of unification.
[SPEAKER_02]: See, like in day-to-day life, reasons for doing something is the un... mind is unified to that extent throughout all the actions of doing that thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you want to, I don't know, drink some tea or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: All the little things you do, preparing tea, getting together, boiling the water, drinking it, it's already unified by the intention to have tea being drunk.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's usually
[SPEAKER_02]: Things that we attend to, pull us away from what we already know.
[SPEAKER_02]: You already know you want to have tea.
[SPEAKER_02]: You already know what tea.
[SPEAKER_02]: You already know everything.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't need to go and...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how... what do you do?
[SPEAKER_02]: I need to take the cup, take the cup, put the bag, put the bag... No.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just do all of that, because it's already unified by the intention to have the tea extracted, basically, from the bag, with the hot water, and you already know how to do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the context is already there, and to that extent, your mind is unified with that purpose.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, now, find even more general purpose.
[SPEAKER_02]: Purpose of not acting out of craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: Make that your context.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that becomes your unified mind upon never acting out of craving in regards to whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: Tea or other things, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: If it's rooted in craving, it's not acted out of.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you clarified that context to the point of actually, yeah, now your mind is unified in it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's already samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: As opposed to the typical thing would be like keep asking yourself why you want to tea while you're doing everything and just distract yourself in the fact that there is something... That's already there.
[SPEAKER_02]: The only reason you can... Why do I want...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's because it was already there.
[SPEAKER_02]: You already know what it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's on that level of discerning what's already there without you needing to attend to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your body postures, or the body as a whole... And, obviously, the more... the more effort you invest in it, it becomes even, like, even more specific things, then, you can be aware of peripherally, without attending to them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, you know, in the beginning, specific things, you know, I must focus, I must focus on this.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the practice of samādhi is opposite direction of practice of focusing.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not unifying things through, like, absorbing in one point, but it's unifying things through finding one point that unifies everything else within it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah, it is one-pointedness.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just one... such a vast point, vast container, that whatever occurs within it is seen against that perspective.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's a very unified mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, overall, then, in that kind of context are the work to be done when there are problems and there are states of craving or craving just arising, not the state, but the craving, is eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: Maintaining the context within which craving is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, like, even if you kind of have gone into the craving, you know, it's not going to start perfect, but you just still have that kind of modus operandus about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: You include that in that context.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, again, it doesn't matter how much you were pulled by the craving and what other things... choices out of craving you made on account of that craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's still within how you feel it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You wouldn't be making choices of getting rid of the pain, if pain is not felt.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, not losing the context of your feeling, otherwise, means being properly mindful of your feelings, regardless of the craving of things done out of craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why that sense restraint and virtue needs to be developed beforehand.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because when that has become your... when your behavior has become behavior of non-physical engagement with sensuality, ill-will and so on, that's how you already form the context.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know what I do, but I know what I will not do.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's already a threshold for your start.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, within that, I know I will not do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let me invest more effort in discerning what I'm doing
[SPEAKER_02]: Within that broader non-doing of non-physically engaging with greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, but I am verbal.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, so let me not do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, it comes the point...
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, so I'm mentally... And mentally, you engage with it when I said...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I will read the suttas and practice dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because I want to get rid of this pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: But not through like...
[SPEAKER_02]: Wait a minute.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in order to get rid of the pain, you need to understand the pain that's here and not try to get rid of it by default.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you'll never see that if your behavior hasn't